Alvin Howell Papers MS160
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Alvin Howell Papers
1950 -- 1980
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Howell, Alvin
MS160
12 Linear Feet 10 boxes and 1 oversized folder
Arrangement
This collection is not processed.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of photographs, correspondence and other papers related to Dr. Alvin Howell's research work with balloons. The collection primarily contains photographs of balloon launches that Howell directed.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Alvin Howell joined the Tufts University electrical engineering department faculty in 1940 and served as the chairman of the department from 1941 to 1970. He led the first team to send an unmanned 400-foot-tall balloon around the world in 1957, a spy flight funded by the Air Force to gather intelligence on the Soviet Union.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Faculty papers; Slides (photographs); Hot air balloons -- Launching; Howell, Alvin
- Additional accessions, 1950 -- 1980; MS160.001; 1 Volumes
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Slides, 1950 -- 1980; MS160.001.GB (Box data_value_missing_7895b037b0187ba7868f5b73396ae225, Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    former barcode 39090015513662g
  - Slides, negatives, and glass plates, 1950 -- 1980; MS160.002.GB (Box data_value_missing_7895b037b0187ba7868f5b73396ae225, Box 2)
    Former barcode 39090015513670g
  - Maps S85 to S167, 1953 -- 1954; MS160.004.GB (Box data_value_missing_d6b1e10f16a46384862cd6a3cbb0ca6f, Box 3)
    File cabinet Drawer 1 (number assigned by DCA); former barcode 39090015514041g
  - S168 1 thru 13 to S235 1 thru 12 (22 Aug 1955) AND S236 1 thru 12 and S291 1 thru 12, 1955 -- 1956; MS160.005.GB (Box data_value_missing_d6b1e10f16a46384862cd6a3cbb0ca6f, Box 4)
    File cabinet Drawer 1 cont. (number assigned by DCA) and the start of Drawer 2; former barcode 39090015514058g
  - S292 1 thru 16 (29 Nov 1956) - S420 1 thru 12 (20 June 1958), 1956 -- 1958; MS160.006.GB (Box data_value_missing_d6b1e10f16a46384862cd6a3cbb0ca6f, Box 5)
    File cabinet Drawer 2 cont. (number assigned by DCA); former barcode 39090015514066g
  - S421 1 thru 12 - S429 1 thru 12 (12 July 1958) AND Correspondence, Contracts S199, Daily Research, Notes, Telephone Conversations, MS160.007.GB (Box data_value_missing_89eb102cbbf33e3a6ddf68e4b83a6d83, Box 6)
    File cabinet Drawer 2 finished (number assigned by DCA) AND Drawer 3; former barcode 39090015514074g
  - S488-3 to S495 - Divider - S430 1 thru 12 - S465 1 thru 29, 1958 -- 1965; MS160.008.GB (Box data_value_missing_89eb102cbbf33e3a6ddf68e4b83a6d83, Box 7)
    File cabinet Drawer 4 (number assigned by DCA); date range is approximate; former barcode 39090015514082g
  - S466 1 thru 14 - S498 1 thru 16 (29 Aug 60) AND Drawer 5 (numbers runs backwards) S509 then up into the teens and down to S503, 1958 -- 1965; MS160.009.GB (Box data_value_missing_89eb102cbbf33e3a6ddf68e4b83a6d83, Box 8)
    File cabinet Drawer 4 cont (number assigned by DCA) and start of Drawer 5; date range is approximate; former barcode 39090015514090g
  - S504 1-9 to S501; G2-246 1 thru 21; Wind screen test AND Telescope Aug 1969 to BAMM II 8 Oct 1979, 1965 -- 1979; MS160.010.GB (Box data_value_missing_ef760045cbe45cbe2bfdd8d842476154, Box 9)
    File cabinet Drawer 5 cont (number assigned by DCA) and start of Drawer 6; date range is approximate; former barcode 3909015514108g
  - BAMMII through 59-170E 1-29, 1970 -- 1979; MS160.011.GB (Box data_value_missing_ef760045cbe45cbe2bfdd8d842476154, Box 10)
    File cabinet Drawer 6 finished (number assigned by DCA); date range is approximate; former barcode 390900155514116g
  - 3F-BO Layouts and Views (unprocessed), 1960 -- 1979; MS160.012.GB (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 3)
    Oversized material in map case; segregated due to mildrew smell; some materials removed from housing and interleaved - envelopes are under respective materials